Guide to the Edward Killoran Brown Collection of Willa Cather
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Edward Killoran Brown collection of Willa Cather
1874-1953
1944-1953
YCAL MSS 490
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.89
(5 boxes)
The collection documents Edward Killoran Brown's research and writing of Willa Cather, Willa Cather: A Critical Biography. The collection contains correspondence, writings, and research notes.
Brown, E. K. (Edward Killoran), 1905-1951
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Margaret Killoran, 1953.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Microfilm service copies are available for: Series I. Correspondence (film number 1044).
Edward Killoran Brown (1905-1951)
Edward Killoran Brown, Canadian professor and literary critic. He published under the name E. K. Brown. Brown wrote several non-fiction books, including his posthumously published biography Willa Cather: A Critical Biography (1953). After Brown's death, LeonEdel, American literary critic and biographer, assisted in publishing the biography.
Willa Cather (1873-1847)
Willa Seibert Cather, American author. Her novels include O Pioneers!, My Ántonia, and The Song of the Lark. In 1923 she was awarded the Pulitzer Prize for One of Ours.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents Edward Killoran Brown's research and writing of the biography of American author Willa Cather, Willa Cather: A Critical Biography. The collection contains correspondence, writings, and research notes. Correspondence includes typescripts and copies of letters from Cather to various individuals, and letters to Brown from various individuals. The material was compiled by Brown in the course of his work on Cather.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1874-1950. II. Writings, 1947-1953.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- United States; Biographers -- United States -- 20th Century; Brown, E. K. (Edward Killoran), 1905-1951 ( Willa Cather); Brown, E. K. (Edward Killoran), 1905-1951; Cather, Willa, 1873-1947; Edel, Leon, 1907-1997
- Correspondence, 1874-1950, undated; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Letters from Willa Cather
    - Brown, Edward Killoran, 1937-1947 (Box 1)
    - Gere family, 1896-1905 (Box 1)
    - Greenslet, Ferris, 1945 October 30 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes letter from Greenslet to Brown and note on the letter by Edel
    - Hazlewood, Captain, 1946 June 1 (Box 1)
    - Jones, Will Owen, 1896 January 15, undated (Box 1)
    - Southwick, Helen Louise (Cather), 1939-1946 (Box 1)
      Extracts of letters
    - Typed copies of letters and extracts, 1922-1941 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Charles Cather
    - Cather, Mr. and Mrs. George P., 1874 January 22 (Box 1)
      Regards Cather's birth. Includes notes by Edward Killoran Brown and Leon Edel on Cather's birth.
  - Letters to Edward Killoran Brown
    From various individuals regarding Willa Cather
    - A-P, 1947-1950 (Box 1)
    - R-Z, 1947-1950 (Box 1)
- Writings, 1947-1953, undated; Series II; 1.47; (4 boxes)
  - Loose leaf notebook containing Brown's manuscript notes, made during his travels in Virginia and Nebraska, relating to Cather genealogy, together with notes on Willa Cather letters seen by him, and records of his interviews with Cather friends and relatives, 1947-1950 (Box 1)
  - Willa Cather: A Critical Biography
    - Setting typescript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 1)
    - Setting typescript, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Carbon copy of setting typescript prepared by Leon Edel after Mr. Brown's death, indicating the portions written by Brown, and the insertions and alterations made by Edel, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
      With a typed note on the text signed by Edel.
    - Galley proofs, 1952 September; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Galley proofs, 1952 October 3-1953 January 1; 6 (Box 3)
    - Galley proofs, 1952-1953; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - File containing the roughly-typed chapters, with Brown's manuscript notes, miscellaneous manuscript records of his interviews with contemporaries of Willa Cather., circa 1944-1950; 8 folders (Box 4)
    - File containing the roughly-typed chapters, with Brown's manuscript notes, miscellaneous manuscript records of his interviews with contemporaries of Willa Cather., circa 1944-1950; 7 folders (Box 5)